welcome back to 25 minute physiology in
this series will be able to tackle some
of your most interesting and exciting
physiological topics and do it a lot
more depth than your smaller five-minute
series so if you want to one of the five
minute videos those exciting you a
little bit but you kind of want to know
more or hear more details about what's
going on or are seeing a different light
that's why I made the 25 minute series
and this particular election really talk
about lactate metabolism so sit back and
enjoy let's get started with lactic now
it's much easier to interpret some of
these things especially for most you who
I actually don't have any background in
chemistry which is OK is exactly why I
am making this video in OC that do I'm
sure you're gonna actually liked it so
it's much easier to understand these
things if you see them and that's why I
do this with this screencast animations
and little characters and cartoons for
you to help you visualize was actually
happening with lactate metabolism was
going to jump right into it so we have
to understand is lacking is a byproduct
of anaerobic metabolism this means is
being generated from the metabolism of
glucose or sugar or carbohydrate just
for the record the same word basis
thing if we look at the chemical
structure heard the name of that fact
there for that matter fact of
carbohydrate is caramel hydrate this
means it is a carbon molecule that has
been hydrated so essentially a carbon
that has h2o attached to it as well the
chemical formula for a carbohydrate is C
68 1206 in other words six carbons and
six walks glucose comes in at six carbon
chain even see your remarks are cartoon
123456 those six carbons are are gone
and Shane there now women go through the
process of anaerobic glycolysis or
simply to lyse were break apart in
Glencoe
course referring to look like also we
split their six carbon molecule in 223
carbon molecules called those carbons
are those molecules pyruvate ok now for
those bug him as an inside job there is
a lot more details whenever you split
atoms from their bond you take some
energy to split the atom apart but then
it gives awesome energy now that
response than that overall balance can
be positive or negative in other words
the reaction component there can either
give off energy or can be a net
requiring of energy in this particular
case in the in regard to human skeletal
muscle physiology particular with
exercise this particular reaction is
exerted on an already gives off energy
so it takes a little bit energy right
here so we're here so the bond between
3rd and 4th carbon for example the
carbon split we had to put some energy
into that system we pop that module into
separate molecules it does give off some
energy you know which is why you see
this little molecule over here in the
corner ATP ok ATP is the energy currency
through all the tabs and for all of
biology doesn't matter he's not okay so
that's what we're looking to get his ETP
Michael so we go through glycolysis
we invest in a little bit of ATP
gay no more so in a little bit positive
but your body is working a little bit
positive it wants being positive so we
can see here's this is not the big
picture
the idea is not to generate Peru paid
well it is but there's not a general ed
P right here we want to do is convert I
really do something else which gives us
real GDP but that requires aerobic
metabolism is start to begin or help you
understand
the relationship between the anaerobic
and aerobic metabolism for some reason
people think these are opposing or you
have one of the other ones bad for the
other one focus on how rosa canina root
works these things are lined up next to
each other one directly helps the other
than beneficial complimentary so now we
created a roommate we have to figure out
how do we deal with it
well what we do with I really depends
entirely on one thing what do our own
two levels if we have sufficient amounts
of CO 2 available to take this pyruvate
we ship it into the mitochondria anytime
you hear mitochondria this is a special
woman who made most of the energy in our
cells this is true again I'm animals
other humans on human doesn't matter
anymore
organism factors can be using a tiny
oxidation or a row nick is the same
basic idea that we're having the use
oxygen ever having to do this in my only
option for location for a lil take this
ship it into the mitochondria like you
can see here this red little blobby
thing and looking into these two little
ass killers now it doesn't matter what
they mean and and i know im getting you
deep into some chemistry here but hold
on tight big picture now is going to
help you understand what really is so he
followed with me here so we made
ourselves going molecules now each one
of these molecules gonna get has been
through some folks will call the citric
acid cycle or the TCA is kind of a big
fancy
generating some staffers EDC the
electron transport chain but the point
is that this is what we're really
working for now this image is actually a
bit deceiving because the ATP molecule
here should be like 10 times one here
because we generate maybe two three four
ATP
here but out here is going to be
something like 10 or 20 times the amount
of ATP created here then we created from
simply anaerobic glycolysis so we can
think of this again as the fact that
we're not really trying to generate ATP
Rome anaerobic glycolysis we're really
trying to generate pyruvate so we can
generate a still we can go through this
citric acid cycle that's really what
we're trying to get out and the reason
02 or accident is so important here is
because of what's happening with these
carbons see how to understand the six
carbon carbon thing so we go back to the
beginning Miller glucose carbon chain
you could split into three carbon
molecules can we call those pyruvate
each one of those payroll then converted
and asked but the asked to call a only
have two carbs so we have to understand
what happened to work hartmans here
because it was everything about your
body in a comment violates our rules you
don't kill me but I guess the basic
understanding your body's not going to
generate or give up a little break up on
break in general Adams wanna break from
the molecule must have something better
to go too well in this particular case
if you have free floating carbon around
in your body is going to function like
your body is not going to put itself in
an environment
enzymes and other things don't function
in an extra set of eyes look I know we
need irregardless of the week and go
through the cracks but I'm only going to
do that if there's something around 90
bond with the car and that happens to be
02 so when you start generating much of
pyruvate what do you do when you start
firing you trying to bring in air most
of what's in their number one concern
right now
that skin areas oxygen you take a deep
breath you bring in 02 the o2 then binds
with this extra carbon that gives you a
little bit of energy to make some idiots
but the point is you generate this
commonality site you then go read the
carbon dioxide out his waist so too was
brought in a natural carbon that was
from sugar and CEO 2002 in co2 apt in
fact if you look closely here at the TCA
cycle website you see there for every
turn the Krebs cycle you generate 20
sites so let's put this whole thing
together you start with the six carbon
who comes against split into two
separate three carbon by rubies each
pirate Vegas Convention in asked to go
away you go from 23 car modules to 22
carbon molecules so we have one oxide
burnt here we have one carbon dioxide
that would be over here if I put it on
the fear then this message is sent
through the cycle and each arm burns 12
carbon dioxide and this one will go
through and burn 12 carbon dioxide so we
start with the six carbon molecules
neend with no carbons a bunch of ATP and
its fine and dandy if we've got a lot of
them to around but when you start doing
high intensity exhaustive exercise you
start generating too much my roommate
when the animal to do you have that can
handle I think this way you generate
you're going to enter a metabolism in
the local exercising muscles so again
you're running up a hill as fast as you
can you start burning and generally
lactating your hamstrings and quads and
blues right you have to though because
the ship in those muscles
happening in that exercising but the
oxygen the you use comes from the ex
outside so I have to breathe in oxygen
transport us through my body
get through my lungs get into my
bloodstream transport into muscle and
then you can take care of this is simply
too slow I'll be sharing way too much
because I'm going to need energy way too
fast as I have to go to our body has to
come up with the separate system that
allows us to handle this well stick with
me here this is a basic happens you take
power roommate he started catching a
hydrogen protons now hydrogen is
advanced doing anything protons
changeable here you have to understand
about hydrogen and it is free floating
around in the world it's called acid and
that's what it means
Phu for the term potential hydrogen I
saw them in the high pH pH is a basic
was there for potential hydrogen which
means a bunch of 300 mins needs a bunch
of acid so here's a body says you're
generating much about it very much of
hydrogen and fast enough to go through
metabolism so we'll start attaching is
hydrogen ions to Paris when we do that
we have a special now call it liked it
that will actually is is it simply a
pair Ruby and holding on to higher so
now feeling this way is likely causing
fatigue
question is lactate causing you to be
tire is that it's fall 2010 the gym next
after a hard workout because I'm sore
like a morgue lactic acid oh well not
only is that not true but lacked it's
not causing you to be
in the first place and it's doing what
we call acting as a buffer it is
stopping you from becoming sick because
it is holding on to what would otherwise
be free
asset so it is stopping you from
becoming another thing it does is an
actual you'll remember that is basically
a que hora de prix digester debris
broken down sugar molecule all I have to
do is get rid of this pesky hydrogen not
just jumping into the system would be a
sitting in the area but I can find some
way to handle hydrogen I had just
converted myself back into power routing
which is an excellent view source I mean
once and pyruvate if we can ship it to
mitochondria were off and running to the
Krebs cycle we generated a bunch of ATP
so we can come up with a way to get that
hydrogen off of it we're gonna have a
very very potent fuel source so how do
we handle this hydrogen so we can get
lactate into fuel for the answer is
there you go again damn turns out not
only is action played very well in
Carbondale plays very well with hydrogen
fact if I bring in a couple of hydrogen
since taking on an oxygen molecule I get
myself and the words right now
perfect chemistry but this is a victim
was showing you what's happening once I
start generating a lackluster increase
in trying to bring in oxygen so I can
handle some of that hydrogen into water
h2o be back into pyruvate now we can do
this in a bunch of different ways if I
can do it directly in the cell itself
allowed to talk about more than just
second
the third thing in the third important
aspect of black to give him my number
one thing above her number two of being
a fuel is it acts like a whore Mar fact
you can take a look at dr. George Brooks
he's done a lot of his work in focusing
on research his research on black paper
probably the last three or more years
but he's he's recognized the fact that
black teen is an important signaling
molecule in wall communicate with the
cell in one community with other tissues
throughout the body is something that
communicates with other tissue very very
important in that perhaps a separate
video showing you the importance of it
as a home for now I actually want to
talk to you can actually read the stuff
if you want more on the podcast I know
pretty recently with doctor on a Patrick
on her platform not found my fitness
stuff when they talk a little bit about
this stuff but I don't think they
certainly didn't do it this beginner
level and they weren't as focused on
this topic so you can check out there
are read by his papers I know he's given
tons of presentations years you to check
out let's talk about using that as a
fuel so one of the things we can do with
it
ship it to not exercising muscle fibers
directly in the actual exercising muscle
what I need is this so say for example
my hamstring is is burning it's on fire
and Jerry bunch of lactate in my hands
very well we're not actually using all
the muscle fibers in my hands right now
there's a thing called the size
principle of your fibers are activated
at the same time not all activated your
absolute maximum protection that's
probably not happening there are some
fibers and they're probably the arrow
early enrollment these loans which the
oxidative fibers that even if they are
act
you've got more capillaries and a lot
more mitochondria and much more likely
they will handle the last stage and
they're gonna say hey look you've got a
bunch of basically pre-register
carbohydrate floating around we can take
it because we have a lot of free money
congress were not bound behind like you
guys bring a lot of free oxygen won't
take the oxen combined is the hydrogen
make water and they now do this right if
your calls to this works as I use with
my college students all the time if
you're not you can see probably relate
to time in your life when maybe finances
work so that time in your life when
basically walking to my class and Afghan
AK can just imagine is your favorite
type of cake ever double chocolate ice
cream with whatever you're looking
entirely 31 cash and in really deep in
the French long and half in a little bit
more in the core well if you're probably
say hey you know what the hell that I'm
taking that keiko just cut the
multi-part off throw that away and I got
free shipping they were some people
maybe if you're not in the college
lifestyle anymore you're like gotten
more done any part of your body is kind
of like that calls you look like garbage
I C three pyruvate with a little bit of
garbage the corner I'll just cut that
off really quick
don't that in the water and move on as
pyruvate I'll take that paper made a run
right back into my brain mitochondria
and we will be looking at that time and
380 if we don't ship it to another
muscle fiber another must entirely right
so we generate hands from the ship it to
the shoulder a finger tips of the toes
of the Neckar somewhere we can also ship
it to a different muscle called our
heart
time and that's why hasn't gained
mainstream public attention when this is
not new information but the heart is
called the ultimate slow twitch fibers
extremely oxidative you more so it can
handle acting no problem
make it back and sugar another we're
very well known place to handle black
tape is the litter so this is a process
called Genesis me formation or so this
is your first the creation of glucose
from an ongoing in this case will take
lactaid and specifically to three car
bombs will take to lactate smashing
together and make a new number is
probably as glycogen until we needed and
we can put it into the blood as and
deliver has a bunch of reasons why you
should do that to one of its main rate
properties in terms this context of the
Liberty ways is to maintain blood sugar
gets low you can get a little bit as
into the bloodstream and probably most
exciting is the brain now most folks
don't realizes this is where it gets
really exciting and generate a lot of
interest when I was four years we've
been teaching undergraduates and
graduates your brain can only use
glucose sugar can well turns out and
your brain and for that matter mater red
blood cells or neurons are all general
acted they're all pretty much
functioning only anaerobically as a fuel
source but as a result of that when you
make a used actually produced and taking
the point of of our brain so we've got
our brain that primarily use fuel but of
course we've known for a long time to
get decades it things like ketone bodies
that can be used as well but now that
you understand that a lactaid is
actually just everyday just under a half
broken down molecule of glucose of
course we can use
acting as a fuel source in our brain as
well as your brain lactate as a fuel so
in fact going back to Dr Brooks work if
I told you right now and i sat on
exercising bike and I give you idea your
right arm and i in that i'd give you
enough supply supply of lactic your body
would take the lactate because it again
you don't have to invest in the
beginning we talked to him when I break
down glucose into pyruvate I do get some
energy but it does cost energy in the
system will likely has the same energy
output
the energy requirement to make and sell
my net balance is much higher
it's much more energetically favorable
ok so your brain is going to look like
it's coming at the same time glucose is
coming in because all of Austin's oxygen
is realization lactate is critical to
brain break the taboo is really really
important for healthy and I'm not going
to bust down the treatment of life
arranging things like that but if you
think about it and we've known for years
that someone who exercises especially
someone does high-intensity exercise
they haven't proved memory he can help
with treatment of depression during
finals week you score better on your
exams helps you remember things when you
study the connection now certainly it's
multi-faceted by one of probably
contributing to the effect that you were
literally fueling your brain better
people talk about you know carbohydrate
loading for your muscles and
replenishing making sure that stopped
off but we forget you need as well
they're actually need to produce
metabolism is well it can't just take
sugar making to be into the same things
going on there that you know if I can
get all this energy to your system to
your brain and houses a sugar in a
predestined her pre metabolize I should
say fashion function I think that some
of the more exciting aspects of lactate
hopefully this video helps you learn
will hopefully the animations created
that took me like a hundred hours to
create
visualizing I'm excited looking for the
future of lactate metabolism hopefully
they will have to come back and add some
more things but what I need some help
from you know hopefully I want to
continue doing things like this I think
its bonds important information so
couple of a machine you get out on the
social media Twitter and Instagram and
dr. any company here and let me know any
questions you have about this let's
continue the dialogue help people learn
educate most important the fire people
to be smarter spend more time with
education so questions you have up there
also a second thing from you and that is
what he wants the next to let me know I
wanna come a much different topics
nutrition
exercise X his movements coaching only
saying so what are you most excited
about learning next what can I do for
you and you can check me out here you
can also check out my new website dot
com there feel free to share the same
around pass and I'll need to get this in
as many people as possible so we can
start educating everyone liked it really
is and the importance of exercising
thanks for now